Anton Shirikov

I am a political scientist working on media, misinformation, polarization, and trust. I also study authoritarianism and elites and institutions in post-communist countries. My research relies on surveys, experiments, network analysis, and other quantitative methods.

EMPLOYMENT

Columbia University, Postdoctoral Scholar in Russian Politics

2022-

EDUCATION

University of Wisconsin–Madison, M.A. (2016), Ph.D. in Political Science (2022)

Dissertation: How Propaganda Works: Political Biases and News Credibility in Autocracies (Co-winner of the Best Dissertation Prize in Comparative Politics, The Department of Political Science at UW–Madison)

Committee: Yoshiko M. Herrera (co-chair), Scott Gehlbach (co-chair), Rikhil R. Bhavnani, Jessica L.P. Weeks, Adeline Y. Lo

Moscow State Institute of International Relations, Candidate of Sciences in Political Science (2007)

European University at St. Petersburg, M.A. in Political Science (2005)

PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

PAPERS

2022. "The Oligarch Vanishes: Defensive Ownership, Property Rights, and Political Connections." *Quarterly Journal of Political Science*, Vol.17, No.4. With John Earle, Solomiya Shpak, and Scott Gehlbach. (Prize for the Best Article in the field of Ukrainian history, politics, language, literature and culture published in 2020–2021, The American Association for Ukrainian Studies.)

2021. "Who Gets Ahead in Authoritarian Parliaments? The Case of the Russian State Duma." The Journal of Legislative Studies.

2020. "Eurasia and Post-Communism: Weasel Words?" East European Politics and Societies & Cultures, Vol.34, No.2. With Yoshiko M. Herrera and Dmitrii Kofanov.

BOOKS AND BOOK CHAPTERS

2023. "The Russian Media." In: Wengle, Susanne (ed.). Russian Politics Today: Stability and Fragility. Cambridge University Press. With Scott Gehlbach and Tetyana Lokot.

2022. "Russia: Muddling Through Populism and the Pandemic." In: Ringe, Nils, and Lucio Renno (eds.). Populists and the Pandemic: How Populists Around the World Responded to COVID-19. Routledge. With Yoshiko M. Herrera and Valeriia Umanets.

2018. "Sovereignty and Regionalism in Eurasia." In: Paasi, Anssi, John Harrison, and Martin Jones (eds.). *Elgar Handbook on the Geographies of Regions and Territories*. Edward Elgar Publishing. With Dmitrii Kofanov and Yoshiko M. Herrera.

1

2013. "Public Administration in Russia." In: Liebert, Saltanat, Stephen E. Condrey, and Dmitry Goncharov (eds.). *Public Administration in Post-Communist Countries: Former Soviet Union, Central and Eastern Europe, and Mongolia*. Routledge. With Dmitry Goncharov.

2010. *Anatomiya Bezdeistviya. Politicheskiye Instituty i Konflikty v Budgetnom Processe Regionov Rossii* [The Anatomy of Inaction. Political Institutions and Conflicts in the Budget Process of Russia's Regions] (in Russian). Saint-Petersburg: EUSP Press.

UNDER REVIEW

"Who Trusts State-Run Media? Polarized Perceptions of News Credibility in Non-Democracies" Under review

"Fake News for All: Misinformation and Polarization in Authoritarian Regimes" *Under review*

"Why Is Trust in Media Low in Post-Communist Countries?" Under review

"Is Postcommunism Over? What Is and Is Not Distinctive About Eastern Europe and Eurasia Three Decades After Communism" (with Dmitrii Kofanov and Yoshiko M. Herrera) *Under review*

WORKING PAPERS

"Is Trust in Media Decreasing? Evidence from the World Values Survey"

"A Model of Censorship, Propaganda, and Repression" (with Scott Gehlbach, Zhaotian Luo, and Dmitriy Vorobyev)

MEDIA

2022. "Russian journalists report the facts about Ukraine. Why do Russians ignore them?" The Washington Post. March 3.

My analysis and commentary have appeared on PBS NewsHour, in The Financial Times, The Washington Post (1, 2, 3), HuffingtonPost, USA Today (1, 2), Politifact, CBC, Portland Press Herald, ABC Radio National (Australia), Press Gazette (UK), PÚBLICO (Portugal), The Daily Dot, Christianity Today, and on Wisconsin Public Radio.

CONFERENCES

APSA Annual Meeting (2020, 2021); MPSA Annual Conference (2018, 2019, 2021, 2022); ASEEES Annual Convention (2017, 2018, 2019, 2020, 2021); NYU-CESS Conference (2021); Political Economy in a Changing World (HSE, Moscow, 2021); Wisconsin Russia Project Young Scholars Conference (2018, 2021, 2022); Communication Crossroads (UW–Madison, 2020); Studying Russia and the Postcommunist World (Columbia University, 2019); Regime Evolution, Institutional Change, and Social Transformation in Russia: Lessons for Political Science (Yale University, 2018); The Annual Meeting of the Society for Political Methodology (2017)

INVITED TALKS & SEMINARS

Smith College, 2022; Bourse & Bazaar Foundation, 2022; University of Chicago, 2022; University of Helsinki, 2021; Kyiv School of Economics, 2020

2 2/4

PUBLIC LECTURES

"Russian Invasion of Ukraine and Kremlin's Propaganda" (Kiwanis Club of Downtown Madison) 2022

"Who Believes Propaganda? Media and Politics in Russia" (Participatory Learning and Teaching Organization at the Division of Continuing Studies at UW–Madison)

"Russia's Strategies in Foreign Elections: What Does the Kremlin Want?" (A workshop for Wisconsin educators)

AWARDS

Best Dissertation in Comparative Politics, University of Wisconsin–Madison

2022

2020

Facebook Foundational Integrity and Impact Research Grant (\$50,000, with Yoshiko Herrera, Mingcong Pan, and Yiming Wang). Project: "Understanding the Effects of Digital Restrictions on Affective Polarization"

Summer Dissertation Scholarship from the Department of Political Science at UW–Madison 2021

ASEEES Summer Dissertation Writing Grant (\$6,000)

Summer Initiative Award from the Department of Political Science at UW–Madison 2021, 2020, 2019, 2017, 2016

Graduate student research award from the Center for Russia, East Europe, and Central Asia at UW–Madison (\$4,000)

Harriman Institute Research Grant (\$16,000; joint with Georgiy Syunyaev). Project: "Learning about Bias: An Experiment on News Consumption in Russia"

Harriman Institute Research Grant (\$10,245). Project: "Perceptions of Media Credibility in Non-Democracies: Evidence from Russia"

University Fellowship, UW-Madison

2015-2016, 2019-2020

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Research Assistant for Yoshiko Herrera (UW-Madison)

2021-2022

Research Assistant for Kathryn Hendley (UW–Madison)

Spring and Summer 2021

Research Assistant for Nadav Shelef (UW-Madison)

Summer 2020

Research Assistant for Scott Gehlbach (UW–Madison)

2016-2018

TEACHING

University of Wisconsin-Madison

PS120: Politics Around the World (undergraduate), Teaching assistant

2019

PS170: Research Methods in Political Science (undergraduate), Teaching assistant 2020, 2018

PS919: Intro to Machine Learning (graduate), Lab instructor

2020

Calculus and probability refresher course (graduate), Instructor

2021, 2020, 2019

3

SERVICE

Peer reviews of manuscripts for American Journal of Political Science, Comparative Political Studies, Post-Soviet Affairs, Problems of Post-Communism, East European Politics, Communist and Post-Communist Studies

Co-organizer of the **Comparative Politics Working Group** for graduate students (UW–Madison) 2019-2022

Graduate student coordinator for the **Comparative Politics Colloquium** (UW–Madison) 2018-2019 Graduate student coordinator for the **Political Economy Colloquium** (UW–Madison) 2018-2019

PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIPS

American Political Science Association; Midwest Political Science Association; Association for Slavic, East European, and Eurasian Studies (ASEEES)

SOFTWARE

R, Python, Stata, SQL, LaTeX, RMarkdown, HTML, Shiny, Plotly, Git, Qualtrics

OTHER EXPERIENCE

I have extensive experience of working as a journalist and editor in Russian independent media. For several years, I have served as deputy editor-in-chief and editor-in-chief at Slon.ru, and as opinions editor at the RBC news agency. I have also worked as editor at McKinsey & Company (all in Moscow, Russia).

REFERENCES

Yoshiko M. Herrera, Department of Political Science, University of Wisconsin–Madison, yherrera@wisc.edu

Scott Gehlbach, Department of Political Science and Harris School of Public Policy, University of Chicago, gehlbach@uchicago.edu

Rikhil R. Bhavnani, Department of Political Science, University of Wisconsin-Madison, bhavnani@wisc.edu

4 4/4